Hello,
this is team 23.
This is our final project video,
and this is what we will talk about here.
This is an era where baseball heavily relies on data science,
but most current analyses are
primarily based on mathematical statistics.
We believe these analyses overlook the impact of
the game context and fail to uncover more abstract features,
such as the synergy between the pitcher
and catcher,
or how a pitcher's strategy shifts depending on the count.
To address this,
we employ RNN models,
comparing various data slicing methods and different
model stacking approaches,
aiming to detect the hidden insights that are not immediately
apparent in the raw data.
Okay,
I'm going to talk about data collection.
We easily use the package called PyBaseball,
and when we read the documentation,
we find
Now that we can easily input the first name,
last name,
also the start date and end date,
and then we can get the CSV,
and this is the raw data structure.
Now I'm going to introduce data pre-processing.
We normalize the numeral feature such as
release,
speed,
launch,
angle,
and hit distance.
Then we use one heart to handle categorical feature
like pitch type,
stripes,
balls,
and zone.
And then we add the inferencing feature.
we add additional features based on the frequency of different piece types.
Next up,
I'm going to talk about our model design.
Our first model is an RNN-based model.
The masking layer is to help ensure that
padded values in each sequence are ignored.
The dropout layer helps prevent overfitting.
The two normalization layers is to help accelerate our convergence.
Our second model is an LSTM-based model.
The two-layer LSTM helps our model to learn hierarchical representation.
Our third model is based on the second model,
but with attention layers added.
Our attention is implemented with the following formula,
and it's an additive-based attention.
Our first model is a specialist model,
where we have a normal model which helps predicting the festival pitch types,
and a specialized model helps predicting off-speed pitch types.
And finally,
we have a voting system that takes in the input from those two models
and outputs our final prediction.
Experiment to address the limited data size,
we adopted a slicing technique inspired by
reference paper.
We used beta-based and data-based as criteria for slicing to increase the data size.
For example,
if the minima subsequence length is two and the max length is three,
and we
get this,
this,
and this subsequence and add this subsequence to our data set.
For our data splitting part,
our data is split with the following ratio.
And note that our training plus validation set and our testing set are split without
breaking the temporal order.
This is because otherwise,
subsequences in the training set
might contain future information of our testing set.
And finally,
our subsequences in each of
Closed sets are randomly shuffled.
Here are the results of each prediction model for 3 pitchers.
Starting with Shota Imunaga,
a starting pitcher.
We used BayerServe as a baseline,
and used SimpleRNN,
LSTM,
and LSTM with Attention as models.
The SimpleRNN demonstrated significant improvements that reduced loss and increased accuracy.
Next,
for Hunter Green,
a starting pitcher too.
We observed that their three advanced models did not significantly improve accuracy.
However,
among these models,
LSTM with ATTENTION performed the best.
Finally,
for Mason Miller,
a relief pitcher,
he achieved the highest prediction accuracy among the three pitchers.
Simple RN and LSTM with ATTENTION stood out in particular,
performed exceptionally well.
Okay,
so now let's go through some discussion.
The first thing is that the accuracy in lotteries are not enough to evaluate models.
At first,
we really rely on it to train models,
but after generating some confusion metrics,
we find out that we uncover a really significant issue,
is that the models just frequently
predict fastballs in all the cases,
even the ground truth is other pitch types.
And we think that the behavior happens because the fastball are the main pitch type for most
of the pitcher,
and we can prove it by these distribution figures of our three pitchers
we used.
To address this issue,
after reading some papers,
we add a specialist model which focuses
on less frequent pitch types,
while the original model still exists to handle general cases.
Then using a voting method to decide which model output to choose,
while the overall
accuracy doesn't really improve a lot,
we can still find that not only reduce the probability
of wrong predicting the fastball in wrong time,
but also has a better ability to predict
less frequent pitch types such as splitter or curveballs.
The second point is that the LSTM or adding the attention layer do not really outperform
on the short sequence by results as below.
And actually our sub-sequence range from the two to six pitches,
which are relatively short,
so that the long-term memory advantage of LSTM
do not really fully utilize.
And it may even cause some potential bias accumulation,
which means that it over-emphasize the patterns
or over-focus on high-frequency inputs like fastball
and neglect lots of other pitch types.
Okay,
let's talk about conclusion.
The first thing is that our model outperformed
Bayes' baseline,
which is really good,
you know?
And the second thing is that our model performed better
when pitchers have fewer pitch types
like Miller or Green.
but our model still remains solid and not bad
when the pitcher have more pitch types like Shota Imanaga.
And our model really have some practical value.
It's that they provide a powerful tool
to analyze the pitching tendencies and some strategies.
For pitcher and coaches,
they can use it to check
that if there are some maybe subtle differences
between maybe release points or predictable sequences
might allow batter to guess pitches.
And addressing this issue can make pitcher
have better performance.
And for catchers,
they can use this model to check that if there are
really some habit patterns when they are calling set strategies.
And this can help them to have a
better performance.
And that's it.
Thank you for listening.
And we're team 23.